Guide to the Herbert H. Lehman papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Herbert H. Lehman Papers,
1858-1963
Lehman, Herbert H. (Herbert Henry), 1878-1963.
1,250,000 items.
Columbia University. Herbert H. Lehman Suite and Papers, New York, NY.
4078518
Biographical Note
Lehman was Lieutenant Governor of New York, 1928-1932; Governor of New York, 1933-1942; Director General of the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA), 1943-1946; Senator of New York, 1949-1956; and partner in Lehman Brothers, 1908-1928.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts of writings, documents, sound recordings, motion pictures, political cartoons, clippings, printed material, and memorabilia. These document Lehman's early business career and his careers as Lieutenant Governor of New York, Governor of New York, Director General of UNRRA, and Senator from New York. Also documented are Lehman's college years, his retirement years, and family and personal life. Materials dating from 1858 relate to his father and grandfather. Correspondents include Franklin Delano Roosevelt, Harry S. Truman, Herbert C. Hoover, Dwight D. Eisenhower, John F. Kennedy, Lyndon B. Johnson, Hubert H. Humphrey, Eleanor Roosevelt, and Lady Bird Johnson.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 8 series:
Series I. Special Files
Series II. Correspondence, Memoranda And Related Papers
Series III: Campaign Correspondence and Related Material
Series IV: Clipping Books, Press Releases, Speeches Articles and Statements
Series V: Miscellaneous Papers
Series VI: The Reference Library of The Herbert H. Lehman Papers
Series VII: Films, Tapes And Disk recordings
Series VIII: Memorabilia
Subjects
Herbert H. Lehman Collections (Columbia University); United States.--Congress.--Senate.; New York (State).--Governor.; New York (State).--Office of the Lieutenant Governor.; United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration.; Lehman Brothers.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Johnson, Lady Bird, 1912-2007.; Lehman family.; New York (State)--Politics and government--1865-1950.; New York (State)--Politics and government--1951-; United States--Politics and government--20th century.; New York (State)--Commerce.; New York (State)--Social life and customs.; Families--New York (State); International relief.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.; World War, 1939-1945--War work.; Presidents--United States.; Governors--New York (State); Motion pictures.; Cartoons.; Politicians.; Governors.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
Correspondence, manuscripts, documents, sound recordings, motion pictures, political cartoons, clippings, printed material, memorabilia
Alternate Formats
Pearl S. Buck letters and telegrams are on microfilm.
- Series I. Special Files
  - Subseries I.1: Correspondence Files 1895 to 1963, (7 drawers, ca. 900 folders)
    The Herbert H. Lehman Papers are completely catalogued. The card index catalogue which includes cross references to subjects and correspondents is available for the use of researchers.
    This personal and reference material includes autograph letters from Herbert Lehman's parents and a good many useful biographical documents. One folder is of special interest as it outlines his college career; it is a series of letters from his older brother Arthur Lehman written between 1895 and 1899. Gift of Mrs. Richard Bernhard, 1966.
    The correspondence with two of Herbert Lehman's biographers, Allan Nevins and William V. Shannon, contains valuable additions to their research files which are in the library of the collection (see The Reference Library of the Herbert H. Lehman Papers.).
    There is also excellent material concerning UNRRA in this file, particularly a series of letters from Herbert Lehman to Mrs. Lehman written while he was on overseas missions, and a brief history of UNRRA by Commander Sir Robert Jackson, Deputy Director-Ge neral, which gives a fine outline of the work of the organization.
    The special file now also includes correspondence with the most important people who were connected with Herbert Lehman's career. It contains the correspondence with Franklin D. Roosevelt and Harry S. Truman which was not mounted in albums (listing of mounted material). It also contains the complete correspondence with Presidents Herbert C. Hoover, Dwight D. Eisenhower, John F. Kennedy, and Lyndon B. Johnson, and with Vice President Hubert H. Humphrey. There is a large correspondence with Eleanor Roosevelt and a number of letters of Lady Bird Johnson. It should be noted that the Kennedy, Johnson, and Humphrey files date from the time when all three men were colleagues of Herbert Lehman in the United States Senate., [v.p.], 1895-1962
    [This was originally a small special file for particularly important or personal letters that Herbert Lehman wished to use for personal reference or did not want in the general files at a certain time.]
    - Americans for Democratic Action
    - American Jewish joint Distribution
    - Committee American Labor Party
    - Dairymen's League
    - Democratic National Committee
    - Joint Distribution Committee
    - New York: Young Democratic Club
    - Palestine Economic Corporation
    - Williams College
    - Milton E. Krentz, 1967
    - Professor Maurice F. Neufeld, 1966
    - Judge Edward Weinfeld, 1966
    - Dean G. Acheson
    - William Benton
    - Adolf A. Berle, Jr.
    - Chester Bowles
    - Benjamin N. Cardozo
    - James B. Carey
    - Josephus Daniels
    - Paul H. Douglas
    - David Dubinsky
    - John Foster Dulles
    - James A. Farley
    - Thomas K. Finletter
    - Edward J. Flynn
    - Homer Folks
    - Felix Frankfurter
    - Arthur L. Goodhart
    - C. J. Hambro
    - Joe R. Hanley
    - W. Averill Harriman
    - Leon Henderson
    - Lister Hill
    - William Hodson
    - Paul G. Hoffman
    - Harry L. Hopkins
    - Harold L. Ickes
    - Hugh R. Jackson
    - Robert H. Jackson
    - Sir Robert G. A. Jackson
    - Philip Jessup
    - Estes Kefauver
    - Robert F. Kennedy
    - Fiorello H. LaGuardia
    - Henry Morgenthau
    - Henry Morgenthau, Jr.
    - Wayne Morse
    - Richard L. Neuberger
    - Maurice F. Neufeld
    - Allan Nevins
    - Lithgow Osborne
    - Frances Perkins
    - Charles Poletti
    - John J. Raskob
    - Walter P. Reuther
    - Anna M. Rosenberg
    - Samuel 1. Rosenman
    - Alfred E. Smith
    - Adlai Stevenson
    - Herbert Bayard Swope
    - Robert L. Wagner
    - Robert L. Wagner, Jr.
    - Lillian D. Wald
    - Edward Weinfeld
    - Walter White
    - Roy Wilkins
    - G. Mennen Williams
    - Democratic National Committee
    - Joint Distribution Committee New York
    - Young Democratic Club
    - Palestine Economic Corporation
    - Williams College
    - Milton E. Krentz, 1967
    - Professor Maurice F. Neufeld, 1966
    - Judge Edward Weinfeld, 1966
    - Dean G. Acheson
    - William Benton
    - Adolf A. Berle, Jr.
    - Chester Bowles
    - Benjamin N. Cardozo
    - James B. Carey
    - Josephus Daniels
    - Paul H. Douglas
    - David Dubinsky
    - John Foster Dulles
    - James A. Farley
    - Thomas K. Finletter
    - Edward J. Flynn
    - Homer Folks
    - Felix Frankfurter
    - Arthur L. Goodhart
    - C. J. Hambro
    - Joe R. Hanley
    - W. Averill Harriman
    - Leon Henderson
    - Lister Hill
    - William Hodson
    - Paul G. Hoffman
    - Harry L. Hopkins
    - Harold L. Ickes
    - Hugh R. Jackson
    - Robert H. Jackson
    - Sir Robert G. A. Jackson
    - Philip Jessup
    - Estes Kefauver
    - Robert F. Kennedy
    - Fiorello H. LaGuardia
    - Henry Morgenthau
    - Henry Morgenthau, Jr.
    - Wayne Morse
    - Richard L. Neuberger
    - Maurice F. Neufeld
    - Allan Nevins
    - Lithgow Osborne
    - Frances Perkins
    - Charles Poletti
    - John J. Raskob
    - Walter P. Reuther
    - Anna M. Rosenberg
    - Samuel 1. Rosenman
    - Alfred E. Smith
    - Adlai Stevenson
    - Herbert Bayard Swope
    - Robert L. Wagner
    - Robert L. Wagner, Jr.
    - Lillian D. Wald
    - Edward Weinfeld
    - Walter White
    - Roy Wilkins
    - G. Mennen Williams
  - Subseries I.2: Special Subject Personal File
    - Material that was kept in Herbert Lehman's desk, or in a nearby cabinet, for ready reference., (2 drawers )
    - American Jewish Conference Bibliography, 1945-1947
    - American Jewish Tercentenary Community Manual, 1933-1934
    - Bank holiday Canavan notes; James A. Broderick material; Gordon A. Rentschler material, 1933-1934, (4 folders,)
    - Campaign clippings, 1950, (8 folders )
    - Campaign material, 1928-1950, (8 folders )
    - Civil rights and civil liberties clippings, (clippings)
    - Democratic and Republican platforms, 1956
    - Depressed areas, Federal aid to, 1956
    - European Recovery Programs, (7 pamphlets)
    - Fulbright Stock Exchange Act (S. 2054), 1956
    - Fund for the Republic
    - Glanzstoff strike, 1929
    - Governor's Advisory Commission Cloak and Suit Industry, 1925-1926, (9 printed records or briefs, Printed records or briefs)
    - Housing-Amalgamated Project-Lower Manhattan, 1931-1938
      [Including file of correspondence with Aaron Rabinowitz. Gift of Aaron Rabinowitz, 1966]
    - Humane slaughter of livestock, 1958
    - Immigration, (4 folders, 9 pamphlets)
    - Israel, tenth anniversary, 1958, (11 folders)
    - Lake Ontario water levels
    - Lehman, Orin "Report on ECA in Southeast Asia"
    - National Council for Industrial Peace, (2 folders)
    - New York reform politics, (19 folders)
    - New York State Democratic Convention, 1958
    - Phillipines trade, 1956
    - Programs and souvenirs of public events
    - Puerto Rican taxes, 1956
    - Rappaport, Joseph "Principles in Politics", 1958, (Draft)
      [Completion of research report, "Herbert H. Lehman and the Democratic Reform Movement in New York," 1964]
    - Senate Job applications and Bills introduced, 1955
    - Senate Office payrolls
    - Senate Office salaries and job applications
    - Senate Office personnel
    - Senate Problems of constituents, 1956, (2 folders )
    - Senate Security incident, June 1956
    - Senate Voting record and election results
    - Senate Swiss watches, 1956
    - UNRRA, ( 6 pamphlets, pamphlets)
    - "Voice of the People," letters about the Cardinal Spellman- Eleanor Roosevelt controversy, 1949, (2 folders)
- Series II. Correspondence, Memoranda And Related Papers
  - Subseries II.1: General Correspondence
    - 1913-1926, (1/4 drawer )
  - Subseries II.2: Correspondence with Lillian D. Wald and The Henry Street Settlement
    - The fifty-two pieces of this material form an addition to correspondence with Miss Wald and Henry Street which is in the Special Files, (1 folder)
      [Gift of the Henry Street Settlement and the Visiting Nurse Service of New York, 1967 ]
  - Subseries II.3: Correspondence with Carolin Flexner
    - Miss Flexner was Herbert Lehman's long-time personal secretary in New York, and was entrusted with the day-by-day administration of his philanthropic interests., 1921 to 1929, (4 folders)
    - Aid Requests, 1924 to 1940, (One and one-half drawers )
    - Charities, 1924 to 1940, (one half drawer )
      [1/2 drawer ]
    - Correspondence between Edith Lehman and Carolin Flexner, 1926-1940, (3 folders )
  - Subseries II.4: Paul Baerwald Papers
    - Paul Baerwald, a founder and long-time chairman of the joint Distribution Committee, was a good friend of Herbert H. Lehman. These papers illustrate their cooperation on the Committee and in other public works, as well as Mr. Baerwald's other fields of interest. In addition, the Baerwald Papers contain material concerning Hermann Baerwald, 1828-1907, the German historian and educator., 1916-1960, (65 folders)
      [Gift of Mrs. Myron S. Falk, Jr., 1968. ]
  - Subseries II.5: Gereral Correspondence
    - , 1929 to 1931, (1 drawer )
  - Subseries II.6: Lieutenant Governorship Papers
    - Arranged alphabetically for the entire period., 1929-1932, (44 reels Microfilm)
  - Subseries II.7: Correspondence With Franklin D. Roosevelt
    - Additional correspondence with President Roosevelt is in the Special Files., 1929-1944, (3 elephant-folio volumes)
  - Subseries II.8: Correspondence With Carolin Flexner
    - , 1930-1945, (1 drawer )
  - Subseries II.9: General Correspondence
    - , 1932, (Three-quarters of a drawer )
  - Subseries II.10: General Correspondence
    - Arranged alphabetically by correspondent for the entire period. 1933-1940, (17 drawers )
  - Subseries II.11: Governorship Papers
    - Arranged alphabetically by correspondent for the entire period, 1933-1942, (106 reels Microfilm)
  - Subseries II.12: Correspondence With Frank Altschul
    - Arranged chronologically. This collection is an addition to material in the Special Files and in the general correspondence files in this section. Mr. Altschul, the well-known banker and editor, was Herbert Lehman's brother-in-law and close friend., 1935-1960, (11 folders)
      [Gift of Frank Altschul, 1967. ]
  - Subseries II.13: General Correspondence
    - Arranged alphabetically for the combined years, 1941 & 1942, (7 drawers )
  - Subseries II.14: Personal Correspondence of the Director General of UNRRA
    - , 1942-1946, (2 drawers )
  - Subseries II.15: General File of the Director General of UNRRA
    - Arranged alphabetically for the combined years. Included diaries of missions to London, April 1943, and to North Africa and Cairo, March-April 1944, 1942-1946, (25 folders)
  - Subseries II.16: The Hugh Jackson Papers
    - Hugh Jackson was Herbert Lehman's chief assistant during the period of organization of OFRRO and of UNRRA, and was Deputy Director General of UNRRA at the time of his retirement from this work. These papers contain important memoranda, correspondence, and conference reports relative to the setting up of this international organziation., 1942-1946, (29 folders)
      [ Gift of Mrs. Hugh Jackson, 1966 ]
  - Subseries II.17: American Committee for the Protection and Salvage of Artistic and Historic Monuments in Europe
    - Herbert Lehman was a member of this committee, and this material includes his correspondence on committee business as well as numerous releases and memoranda of the committee, 1943-1946, (7 folders)
  - Subseries II.18: Marshall MacDuffie Papers on the UNRRA Mission to the Ukraine
    - Marshall MacDuffie was appointed by Herbert Lehman as the first chief of the UNRRA mission to the Ukraine. These papers include reports, correspondence, memoranda, and a review and history of the work of this mission, 1944-1948, (6 folders)
      [ Gift of Mrs. Marshall MacDuffie, 1968.]
  - Subseries II.19: Correspondence With Harry S. Truman
    - Additional correspondence with President Truman is in the Special Files., 1945-1963, (1 elephant-folio volume)
  - Subseries II.20: General Correspondence
    - , 1946, (1 drawer )
  - Subseries II.21: Correspondence With Frances Bergman
    - Mrs. Bergman succeeded Miss Flexner as Herbert Lehman's personal secretary in New York for philanthropic matters. 1946-1953, (5 folders)
  - Subseries II.22: General Correspondence
    - , 1947, (2 drawers)
  - Subseries II.23: General Correspondence
    - , 1948, (2 drawers)
  - Subseries II.24: Senatorship Papers
    - Sub-subseries II.24.1: Legislative Files
      - Includes staff research reports, correspondence, memoranda, and related material on legislative matters. Some of the more important subjects are: 1949-1955, (30 drawers)
      - Agriculture
      - Appropriations
      - Civil rights
      - Post Office
      - Civil Service
      - Defense
      - Displaced persons
      - Foreign policy and foreign aid
      - Health
      - Housing
      - Immigration
      - Internal Security Bill
      - Labor
      - Minimum wage
      - Post Office
      - St. Lawrence projects
      - Social Security and Welfare
      - Taft-Hartley law
      - Tidelands
      - Tariffs
      - Taxes
      - Veterans
    - Sub-subseries II.24.2: Bill Files
      - Includes copies of Bills sponsored by, or of particular interest to, the Senator, with pertinent correspondence and research notes., 1949-1956, (5 1/2 drawers )
    - Sub-subseries II.24.3: Departmental Files
      - Material and correspondence concerning practically every government department and commission. The last seven drawers are devoted to the State Department alone. The files are divided as follows:
      - Miscellaneous, 1950
      - Postmasters and Armed Forces academies, 1950-1957
      - 1950; 1951; 1951-1952; 1952-1953; 1953-1954; 1954-1955; 1956
      - State Department, 1950-1956
      - The most important subjects represented in this file are as follows:
      - Agriculture
      - Appropriations
      - Hoover Commission and government reorganization
      - Housing
      - Immigration
      - Joseph McCarthy
      - Post Office
      - Railroads
      - St. Lawrence projects
      - Social Security
      - Veterans
      - Welfare
    - Sub-subseries II.24.4: Miscellaneous Files
      - Crank file: correspondence received from mentally ill people, bigots, etc., 1949-1956, (1 drawer)
      - McCarthy and McCarthyism: correspondence and related ma- terial both for and against, 1949-1956, (2 drawers)
      - Postmasters: correspondence on appointments, (1 drawer)
    - Sub-subseries II.24.5: Research Files
      - More than 90 percent of the files are devoted to the following subjects: 1949-1956, (4 1/2 drawers)
      - Displaced persons
      - Housing
      - Immigration
      - Internal security
      - Rent control
      - Social Security
    - Sub-subseries II.24.6: "Robo" Files
      - These files contain a complete run of all form letters sent out by Senator Lehman and his office. There is also a large amount of correspondence relating to each letter., 1949-1956, (8 drawers)
    - Sub-subseries II.24.7: "Tissue" Files
      - Carbon copies of all correspondence emanating from the Senator and his office staff from November 1949 through December 1956. Arranged chronologically by month, with the material for each month arranged alphabetically by correspondent. The final 21/4 drawers consist of duplicates, January 1950 to March 1956, of those carbons which were kept in the New York office for convenience. 1949-1956, (15 1/4 drwaers)
    - Sub-subseries II.24.8: General Personal Correspondence
      - Arranged alphabeticaly by correspondent under each year; these are files from the New York office., 1949-1963
    - Sub-subseries II.24.9: Position Papers
      - Full description on cards of the Senator's positions on government topics, made for the use of his office staff. More than thirty-five subjects are covered. 1950-1956, (1 card index box)
    - Sub-subseries II.24.10: Recommendation File
      - All personal recommendations made and recommendation and personnel data letters received for the period, 1950-1956, (1 drawer)
    - Sub-subseries II.24.11: New York Office Correspondence
      - Arranged alphabetically by correspondent under each year. This general personal material is duplicated to some extent in the file marked General personal correspondence, 1949-1963 above. However both files contain many documents not duplicated, 1950-1963, (15 drawers)
    - Sub-subseries II.24.12: Personal-Official
      - Arranged alphabetically by correspondent under each year, 1951-1956, (4 drawers)
    - Sub-subseries II.24.12: Personal
      - Arranged alphabetically by correspondent under each year. Mainly material similar to personal official papers, 1951-1956 above, but with less official correspondence, 1952-1956, (2 drawers)
- Series III: Campaign Correspondence and Related Material
  - Subseries III.1: Campaign Files
    - Contain a great deal of correspondence, including some about personal and official matters handled in the midst of campaign work. Also articles, campaign material, duplicate speeches, and related material. The drawers are numbered as follows: 1928-1954, (9 drawers)
    - 1. 1928-1936
    - 2. 1936-1949
    - 3. 1949
    - 4.1949-1950
    - 5. 1950
    - 6. 1949-1950 Finance
    - 7. 1949-1950 Miscellaneous
    - 8. 1949-1950 Letters of congratulation and thanks
    - 9. 1954 Wagner campaign
  - Subseries III.2: Campaign Material
    - A large collection of mounted material consisting of campaign "handouts," labels, speeches, reports, lists, instructions to workers, research material, finance, women's division and nationalities division reports, news, clippings including foreign language press, and other campaign miscellany, 1930-1950, (28 looseleaf scrapbooks)
  - Subseries III.3: Campaign Correspondence
    - Material dealing with the campaign of 1932, 1932, (One quarter drawer)
  - Subseries III.4: Campaign Contributions Received
    - Includes the campaigns of 1936, 1946, 1949, and 1950, 1936-1950, (2 card index drawers, 1 notebook)
      [A vast amount of campaign information is found in Sereis IV: Clipping Books, Press Releases, Speeches, Articles, and Statements]
- Series IV: Clipping Books, Press Releases, Speeches Articles and Statements
  - Subseries IV.1: Press Clipping Collection
    - A complete newspaper record of Herbert Lehman's entire public career. The clippings include items selected from state-wide and country-wide papers in addition to all the New York and Washington metropolitan dailies. Copies of his speeches are also mounted in their proper order, and usually the reading copy is mounted with the clipping. There are also some of the originals of the photographs used in the news stories. Some important subdivisions of the collection are: 1924-1964, (199 bound folio-size volumes)
    - "Voice of the People," correspondence from the general public pro or con controversial subjects, (10 volumes)
    - Editorials, (10 volumes)
    - Photographs, (7 volumes)
    - Political campaigns, (19 volumes)
    - Obituary reports and memorial tributes to Herbert Lehman, (2 volumes)
    - Williams College Clippings, playbills, dance cards, tickets, and other souvenirs of Herbert Lehman's college career, 1895-1899, (1 volume)
  - Subseries IV.2: Speeches
    - Speeches, December 6, 1928 through December 31, 1963, (16 looseleaf binders)
    - Speeches, January 1, 1946 through December 31, 1963, (5 drawers )
    - Campaign speeches and news releases, 1946-1950, (5 scrapbooks, 5 volumes)
    - Speech reference index: this is a valuable aid for locating speeches, and positions on specific subjects mentioned in Speeches, 1949-1955, (2 card index boxes)
  - Subseries IV.3: Articles By And About Herbert Lehman
    - Periodical and newspaper articles, both biographical and autobiographical, including a number of Congressional Record reprints and also memorial material of 1964. See VI. Library for bound material of this type., 1928-1964, (1 drawer)
  - Subseries IV.4: Statements
    - Statements given mainly in answer to specific requests, with pertinent correspondence, 1928-1964, (1 drawer)
  - Subseries IV.5: UNRRA Documents
    - Documents, charts, minutes, press releases, and miscellaneous material, 1942-1946
  - Subseries IV.6: Press Releases
    Gifts of copies of speeches and articles by or about Herbert Lehman have been received from the following: Professor Julius C. C. Edelstein, 1967-1968. Miss Jessica Feingold, 1965. Dr. Joseph Rappaport, 1965